welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we call hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
all right everyone welcome to the stoah
I am Peter Lindbergh the Stewart of the
stoah some of you may know I run a stoic
group in Toronto Canada and obviously we
can't meet in person at the moment so
I've launched the stoah I am seeing the
stoah not only as a place to talk and
practice our stoicism surely some of
that will happen but I'm viewing it as a
digital campfire for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment today my
good friend John Verve a key is going to
share his latest thoughts on the the
meaning crisis and how it relates to
this unfolding kovat 19 situation at
first I suggested to John we call this
meeting the the meaning opportunity than
the meeting Kairos mainly because I've
been hearing a lot of people in the
circles John and I run in saying that
they have a new sense of meaning in this
moment when I mentioned that to John
John crudely suggested that we should be
careful in conflating what feels
meaningful to what feels urgent hence
the reason for the question mark of
today's title so in a more mode I'll
hand it over to John and how this
session works today after he shares his
thoughts
I'll ask him some questions and we'll
open up for the group for questions if
you have a question write it in the chat
box and I will unmute you and then just
read your question to John if you prefer
I read your question then just indicate
that when you write it in the chat box
and we'll go for about 60 minutes if it
goes a little bit over maybe 75 minutes
if that's okay with everyone so that
being said I will hand it over to John
right now
let's see I might have to mute you John
hold on can you meet yourself right now
John unmute yourself me now yep
can hear you great great okay excellent
we had me both uses so thank you for
inviting me Peter and I'm very intrigued
by the question that's coming up for me
right now and so I guess what I want to
do is explore what's happening right now
and how it might be intersecting with
the meeting crisis so one thing that
comes to mind is that one thing we might
expect is that people are experiencing a
lot of reciprocal narrowing their lives
are getting narrowed their agency and
their flexibility is narrowing arm
they're experiencing kind of dama side
in which a lot of places that they
thought of as their home and where they
belong where they worked are getting
truncated and of course that is
happening and I'm talking to people that
are experiencing this rather intensely
we might also see people commenting to
experience this and a really challenging
manner in that they're being sort of
thrown back onto the subjectivity in a
way that could call the way that
subjectivity from Descartes on has been
so central to us that's had such
normally a normative authority for us
and finding that the that subjectivity
does not have that much resources to
provide them with what they need to
confront the radical changes both the
immediate ones and potentially the more
abstract long-term ones that they're
facing
so we could see that happening we could
see as Peter mentioned people all
expressing
a tremendous amount of meaningfulness
coming out and this could be due to a
couple of things this could be due to
just the urgency we could be dropping
down Maslow's hierarchy of needs and
we're actually really not dealing with
meaning in life issues we're dealing
with solving a lot of very concrete
problems and so our problem-solving
machinery is getting sort of current
satisfaction that could be happening and
that could be part of what I was
alluding to when I mentioned to Peter we
might be confusing urgency with meaning
it could be that as people are being
crunched downward and they're losing a
lot of the things and this is more of a
crooked Guardian point it kept us busy
and distracted and in meshed in things
that we thought would give us a sense of
meaning and happiness we can we've
discovered perhaps that we can lose a
lot of this and we are forced into the
interpersonal relationships which is
what we're doing right now as being the
locus where we're trying to satisfy our
need for meaning we're finding that this
is actually a better place to try and
find meaning than the other things we
were doing before so we could be
experiencing an increased of meaning
because of a recovery of the being mode
that is actually present in dialogue we
could be covering recovering meaning
because we and I've seen people doing
this we fall into a kind of nostalgia a
myth or what I might call a mythological
nostalgia the the virus is kind of like
you know a Greek or an Old Testament
deity it's this pervasive ubiquitous
thing out there chaotically sort of it's
like a hyper object use Morton's term
moving through the world and just and
changing and altering things but in an
abstract way and behind the scenes and
it seems to be demanding a purity code
from us a tremendous purity code it
feels a lot like an Old Testament deity
and so that kind of nostalgia and let's
not forget that this is deeply woven
whether or not we're religious is deeply
woven into our
cognitive grammar so people might be
picking up on that and finding the fact
that they're in this kind of
mythological narrative very meaningful
to them
people might be finding it meaningful
precisely because they think this has
provided the final evidence for the need
for their particular pseudo religious
ideological utopia which they are
certain is on the horizon there and much
like the people that Frankel talked
about in in the camps who were certain
of when they were going to be liberated
and then they of course turned out to be
the people once the date had passed they
of course collapsed and often tried
other people down with them so what I'm
saying is I think it's more plausible
and this is why I like the term Kairos
that we're in a situation in which we're
having a very complex set of reactions
to what's happening right now I think
some people are finding an exacerbation
of the meeting crisis in ways that
articulated I think people are maybe
perhaps confusing meaning and urgency
people might be recovering the meaning
of the being mode in the as things get
punched down to interpersonal dialogue
people might be recovering meaning in a
way that I think is dangerous because
they are falling into a well-worn and
well understood although not very
explicitly in their consciousness
explicitly aware mythological narrative
of these kinds of mythological somewhat
demonic forces at work in the world and
so I think it's one of the things we
need to do very carefully is question in
a penetrative fashion what this what the
what the various experiences of the
increase or decrease in meaningfulness
are and when we come to a better
approximation of that complexity coming
to a decision about how we can best
interact with the car Ross because I do
think that there is a real potential
here because the Kairos content
- towards the good or towards the evil I
think there's a there's a real
opportunity here to see our cultural
cognitive grammar shifting in a
fundamental way I'm not necessarily
saying it's gonna happen but I think
there is the real potential for this to
happen and I think there's a real need
for this to happen because I think it is
highly probable that this is not our
last pandemic all of the factors that
have caused this pandemic are still in
existence then still growing this
pandemic was predicted it has been
predicted multiple times in the last
decade and the factors upon which that
successful prediction were made are
still in existence and accelerating and
I think it's highly likely that we will
come into it and I do not think it will
be a merely additive effect the second
pandemic I think it will be an
exponential effect on the way it shakes
things up and causes sort of horrific
exposure to the possibility of a
fundamental training change in our
worldview so that's my thinking right
now and that's the kind of thing I'd
like to explore with you guys great so
I'll warm drum up with some questions if
you have questions you start writing in
the chat box and then I'll call you up
or read it on your behalf so my first
question John so John and I have a
regular circling practice and I only
have spoke to you once and our practice
kind of is on hold at the moment so just
to get in like a really embodied state
I'm curious how since it started dawning
on the collective unconscious that this
is is going to be this is a big deal how
did it affect you personally and in the
body sense so that's very good very good
question so part of the way that became
very salient to me was the extra
stressor on me so one and part of it is
just my own sort of apprehension about
what's going on
part of it was picking up on the stress
it was inducing in the people that I
care a lot about because they faced real
risk in important ways and part of it
was also an existential issue because I
was
struggling to understand how to be
rational in the face of so much
uncertainty and so much shifting
information I was keenly aware of the
fact that you know the representative
bias and the confirmation bias and their
you know and the availability heuristic
we're kicking in and causing me to give
wildly inappropriate judgments of the
probability of things and and I was also
aware of the fact that it was difficult
for me to devote the time needed in
order to determine the plausibility of
some of the information I was given and
I was also aware of the fact that this
was not something for which I could
merely sort of wait because of the
urgency of the risk and my actions could
definitely put other people at risk so
my existential issue will as sort of in
competition with the stressors and also
the concern I have for the people that I
care about and who are in my care and
what that has resulted personally for me
is an elevation of my Meniere's disease
in my left ear which has been very
troubling and trying for me and so I've
had to do quite a bit to moderate that
and I've also decided the way I can
intake action is to take all of the
reasonable precautions that are being
advised to me from people I respect both
personally because they have the rent of
the requisite medical and health
training and from the scientific
community and then beyond that turn to
what can I do to make a difference which
is one of the reasons why I'm here right
now it's one of the reasons why I've
started teaching my meditation course
online for free I started that on Monday
and it's phenomenologically what that
has meant for me in terms of embodiment
is my ability to take action in a way
that I'm being told by others is
mattering to them and making a
difference has significantly reduced my
stress so
and then I came to a decision point this
came out in a discussion I had with
Andrew Sweeney and Christopher master
Pietro that in the end my survival my
just raw bear survival they this is a I
guess a Socratic principle is not worth
sacrificing every other principle for
which I live and so if it comes to a
place where I have to expose myself to
biological risk because principles that
I very much care about are being put at
risk then I've decided that that's in
fact what I will do and you and I we've
been texting about this and I know
Jordan you've been talking about it how
this could be a moment to ride liminal
ride the wave of the liminal oh that
well so so that's again and that that's
something that that's something maybe I
should have brought it up in your
previous question but it maybe it
belongs here because this whole
discussion that I've been having with
Jordan it sort of bridges between my
personal phenomenology and a broader
sort of theoretical interest which is
this idea that Jordan and I have been
exploring of course in one sense it's
connected to the religion that's not a
religion that we've already been to
talking about but it's also connected
with giving people a formulation for a
kind of deeper response to what's going
on here and this is an idea of trying to
reformulate if I'm not quite happy with
the next adjective I'm going to use but
it's the best ones for right now try to
reformulate a post religious sense of
faith what I call Socratic faith and
what does that look like and it's very
much this idea of shifting faith from
some sort of closure and conviction arm
in instead onto this idea of an ongoing
um continuity of contact with an ongoing
unfolding process within reality such
that one is able to sense a Kairos when
it's able to sense the course of events
and one develops a always emerging
always evolving finesse
with how to steer one's way through that
and so we are trying to come up with
because this is of course exemplified in
the Socratic dialogues the way Socrates
is always you know a lover of wisdom in
in on the course of wisdom but he never
claims any kind of completion or closure
upon it and you can see the way think
he's willing to follow the argument
wherever it goes and so that kind of
faith I think is the kind of faith we
need right now and I I'm exploring it
precisely because of what we talked
about already earlier I'm concerned
about the kinds of faith that might be
triggered right now obviously there's
you know two kinds of nostalgic faith
one is the faith in like I say the
mythological God a demonic God out there
another is a nostalgia for let's just
get back to normal as fast as we can
let's just get back to normal as fast as
we can and also the utopic faith the
person who is convinced they have
closure now because they have certainty
as to where the future is going and how
it's going to unfold and I think both of
those kinds of faiths are potentially
very maladaptive and so part of what
I've been trying to do is stitch
together my own phenomenology in the
distress that I've been facing with that
those theoretical concerns in the
discussions but having with Jordan yeah
that's really really good
and it seems like in his liminal space
and as emerging culture wars happening
with those narratives that you just
mentioned yes yes you can already see it
happening one of the things I was
worried about in christen I've spoken
about this we've already seen the
emergence of conspiracy theories that
are starting to gain traction as a way
of of trying to explain as I and I you
know I personally had one thrown at me I
was I did a talk with Greg on reeks we
just posted it and you know one person
was basically you know the invective was
that it's the intellectuals and the
scientists and the theorists like me
that have actually brought us into this
situation right now and so oh it's like
yeah
that's very very dangerous that we start
getting into this kind of conspiratorial
narrative so I'm gonna follow people to
read out their questions again we have
about 60 people on this chat so we're
not gonna get to all the questions and
if you didn't indicate that you wanted
me to read it out then just unmute
yourself and then ask your question to
John so the first question is Jordan you
talked about a silver or silver lining
if you can unmute yourself and just ask
your question - John sure hey so I'm
gonna quickly find it so my question is
basically do you think although this is
a bit of a chaotic statement but do you
think there's somewhat of a silver
lining in that the instant immediacy of
everything that's happening relative to
the ordinary sorts of concerns that
we're being told to to be thinking about
all the time for the media and so on
maybe the silver lining is that it's
somewhat of like a relief to people's
consensus addiction or certainty
addiction which i think is one of the
things that really drives people to get
attached to these old like legacy
sense-making or like information
laundering infrastructures right right
right I think I think that's right I
think the capacity for this to challenge
the obvious Ness of common sense which
how I would put what you're saying and
the way that has been often raised to an
almost sacred level in our discourse the
way that's invoked and it's often a
cover for as you said you know very well
established ways of thinking of often
also cover for very bias for the
operation of bias and trying to protect
it from any critical examination that's
also at work I think the the virus has
the the real I think it is doing this so
it's more than the potential but it has
an ongoing potential that's being
actualized to challenge that that
authority in a profound way and
that in and of itself I don't know if
that in itself is a silver lining
because it's like criticality in a
system we're destabilizing the system
and that of course is what I'm trying to
get out with this Kairos it opens up
possibilities but it opens up multiple
possibilities so when people get their
worldview challenged one of the things
they can do is double down even so you
know the you know the you know the the
evidence of cults right so you have a
cult and it will prophesy the end of the
world and that that prophecy will gain a
certain number of it adherents and then
the prophecy fails and what you what you
might expect is well that would cause
the cult to bleed away but what actually
happens is the cult doubles down and it
expands in size the doubling down they
say oh nobody were wrong and it's a
weird phenomenon that people you'd think
that the failure would be enough to get
people to abandon and reject but instead
they double down and that doubling down
gives them a kind of attractive
confident confidence that sucks people
in uh and so this in fact reliably
happens it usually takes a third or a
fourth failure for the for the movement
to fall apart which is why I'm saying
well I think the next pandemic could be
the really crunchy one now III don't
have any foreknowledge of this it could
go the way you're suggesting it could be
just this wakes people up and they see
the silver lining but like I said
there's clear evidence for and I gave
you some of it that people can go the
other way and that's a concern for me
hmm
so Alex s you had a question about death
and Kairos yeah can you guys hear me yep
great thanks Peter and thanks John for
uh for your talk I was wondering if you
could talk a little bit about the
meaning of Kairos and especially in the
present moment and especially as it
relates to the notion of death so
currently we're in the situation where
we're facing you know the possibility of
death is in view and if collectively
also individually and we know the
probabilities you know are different for
different age groups and so on but that
is kind of in the air yeah I think that
in the existentialist tradition which
remember kind of alluded to earlier that
connection is drawn between you know
kind of authentic existence and
Heidegger potentially yeah yeah how many
if you could say maybe more about that
and especially as it relates to you know
trying to have a more rational wise
approach to the situation you know
rather than going - yeah thanks that's a
great question and I want to answer to
that and III think you're one of the
things that's really interesting
mr. does this and her book beyond fate
and she actually holds out stoicism in
connection with this because the we we
have this word fatal and we accept we
associated with death in particular but
what we've come to do is it's like the
way we think of mad as being angry we're
mad of course means losing your sanity
and one of the things that could cause
you to lose your sanity is your anger
fatality originally meant the way
reality muumuus of its own accord the
hands of fate in that sense no not in
some magical sense but in the sense that
the universe is unfolding for things
beyond our can and it will behave the
way it's going to behave for its own
reasons right and and and so death um
was just one very significant instance
of the fatality of all things that and
visitor talks about the fact that
stoicism tried to pull apart that by
making a distinction between the things
that are largely in the grip of nature
and then the meaning we give them which
has to do you know with our cognitive
processing and our framing and pulling
those apart she said was one of the you
know the deepest ways of trying to get
people to be able to accept the fatality
of all things because the fatality
actually
points to a deep confusion between the
meaning and the event now the
interesting thing about that is you see
of course this being taken up by both
Nietzsche and Kierkegaard especially and
the way in which I think we can stitch
together this notion of fatality and the
and the themes you brought out around
things like authenticity is that um
there's a way in which the fatality of
all things is present with us always
which is our mortality and our mortality
doesn't mean the event of our death it
means that like everything else we are
deep even our own bodies and you see
this in stoicism right even our own
bodies are subject to that kind of
fatality that's what the virus can show
we think we've made health into a God
and we are the masters of our health
well no we're not no or not right I mean
we can make we can move things around
and we can share probabilities but
whatever narrative we have for ourselves
in our bodies the the universe is going
to unfold in our bodies independently of
that narrative so the are the we can we
can deal with the one of the first and
primary ways we have to deal with the
fatality of all things is we have to
deal with it insofar as our own bodies
our own fame our own status which is our
mortality which is different than just
the event of our death
and I think one of the things that the
virus can potentially do for us is make
us step back and become mortals again
which is a very different project than
what we have tried to be for a long time
through the way we manipulate media and
image which is we behave it act as if
we're immortal and then when it becomes
clear that we are in fact mortal we are
we are disenfranchised packaged away
removed from media you know etc etc and
I think instead if we could come to a
place where we can reimburse our
mortality I think that would be a good
way for extending the notion of
authenticity off of just being true to
oneself which i think is a very poor
frame
authenticity and get it getting it back
to living with the fatality of all
things in as rational a manner as
possible that's how I would answer that
question I jump in with it just a quick
follow-up please please
so I'm wondering that would you would
you align the existential tradition more
or less with stoicism I don't need your
son always stoic yeah well yes and no
because you know the Nietzsche's deeply
influenced by stoicism and you know in
kirkegaard writes his PhD dissertation
on Socrates so there's obviously at
least a deep Socratic influence in
crypto garden so both of the you know
the godfathers of existentialism I think
are deeply influenced by this current
however I would not I would not identify
stoicism with existentialism because
existentialism I think and I'm sorry I
mean the posts are trian sense of
existentialism not what's going on in
Heidegger because Heidegger is a
different thing Heidegger is you know we
are the beings whose being is in
question that's a that's a different
thing but the the the the the strand it
comes out later at least one strand of
existentialism that sort of became more
prominent was the idea you know that you
know that our existence precedes our
essence because we are the creatures who
completely decided our essence so
there's a there's a shift from Heidegger
from us being the beings whose being is
in question to us being the self
defining beings and stoicism I think is
much more careful about that we're not
completely self defining beings there's
a lot of there's a lot of about us over
which we have we do not have control as
epictetus famously pointed out and so
whereas
self-definition gets becomes quite
significant maybe even inflated in
certain search me and like strands of
existentialism and you and you lose that
that you know you lose that that that
we're inherently in question I think
stoicism has much more of you know it's
not that we're completely self defining
it's more that we can aspire to a kind
of universal logos a universal
rationality that is the prop the proper
response for our confrontation with
fatality so that's how we pull them
apart okay so I'm gonna read this
question on behalf of Isaiah's you
mentioned conspiracies but I'm wondering
how we can as regular people relate to
the elites at a moment like this it's
it's becoming clear that those more
fortunate have quicker access to testing
for the virus eg Prince Charles NBA
players Hollywood actors yep so this is
always the the trick around this sorry I
didn't mean trick in the sense of
deception I'm in it in the sense of them
you know the the the the thing that
requires finesse so how do you identify
how do you distinguish identifying bona
fide socio-economic let's use that as a
broad socio political socio-economic in
justices unfairness how do you
distinguish them from conspiratorial
thinking and and I guess the idea well
this is what I do I have a heuristic is
that I don't believe in in conspiracy
theories until I get you know evidence
of them that's as good as any scientific
theory or beliefs moves in that
direction
so if you get here you know if you get
undisputed evidence that people have
this kind of access which i think is
happening no one's calling it into
question
there's no plausible alternative
the nation for the purported nough sit
doesn't invoke any initially implausible
entities in their own right
it belongs to an already plausible
history of the wealthy and the rich
manipulating things to their own purpose
then I think that's how you sort of make
the decision so maybe I'm what in fact
proposing is we reserved the term
conspiracy theory for something that
gains its exceptions
primarily just because it proposes a
conspiracy that makes sense of what is
otherwise chaotic whereas coming to a
conclusion from a lot of evidence and
argumentation that's convergent are they
plausible rationally excess of
rationally criticized and rationally
accessible that certain groups of people
are behavior being unjustly and
appropriately I don't think we should
call that a conspiracy theory at all I
think we should say no we should say
what it is we have good evidence that
people are acting unjustly and that they
should be criticized and this is and and
and then we should criticize the
structures that have made it so easily
doable for them to engage in such
unfairness and manipulation that's what
I would say to that
so I'm going to read this on behalf of
Nikolas you talk a lot about people
maybe waking up
what actions can we take to help more
people wake up propagate good
information step into dialogue anything
else well yeah I mean so not only just I
mean yeah obviously propagate good
information and that's what I try to do
with the video series and try to do with
a lot of videos but also propagate the
skills I mean that's like Peter by
working so hard I'm trying to come up
with you know you know a pedagogical
program of putting up a various the
psycho technologies into a optimal
sequence for transitioning people
without them having to make huge
investments in a philosophical education
or into a particular ideology or
metaphysics moving them for however
nevertheless from you know oppositional
bad faith confrontational like
argumentation all the way through to you
know a kind of philosophy a-- not
philosophy but a kind of Socratic
dialogue in which they feel fluent and
capable of participating that can afford
them gaining access to the power of
collective intelligence and hopefully
participating in of transforming it into
collective rationality or perhaps even
collective wisdom i think trying to
reverse engineer the psycho technologies
the meta psycho technologies enact and
exemplify them and try to teach them to
others that's why I'm also teaching the
meditation course for free we need to
get not just the information in the
sense I mean II didn't mean just that so
forgive me around imposing on you but we
need to get more than just the ideas out
is what I'm trying to say we need to
actually teach people a broad set of
skills ecologies of practices we need to
start doing it right now and that's what
I'm trying to do and we need to reverse
engineer as MIT we need to reverse
engineering we need to reverse engineer
your missing cyber technologies
precisely like dialectic
it seems like an interesting opportunity
now that a lot of people are on zoom'
and having these conversations to
practice it
yes very much very much Samir you had a
question about the urgency effect yeah I
try to rephrase it with what I've been
said to get back on the meaning Ness and
the Kairos I have them you know like I
don't really understand this Kairos
concept I have the impression is a kind
of Christian I did the way we are seeing
it I'm seeing like it's a kind of
Christian time of apocalypse of the
rapture you know the moment where
everything is like changing but for me
the the Kairos is more a subjective
reality where it is in a chain of of
salience of of meaning of synchronicity
where someone have it as a changing
moment you follow me not completely I'm
not first of all a Kairos doesn't limit
you to the apocalypse the apocalypse are
just a culminating Kairos it is it is a
notion it comes out of the sort of
platonic Christian yeah it's about being
any important turn right being able to
sense where that turn in and participate
in it are the turning of events yeah
yeah but I have the impression that at
least I mean for our society it is this
is if moment not by itself not because
as you said it is just appending me we
can say it's a small one there are gonna
be many others but we are now in a
synchronicity of so many crises that we
have been kicking the can down the road
that this is like the drop that is that
is you're feeling the jar you know and
also I would say that the
the urgency thing is that it's too fast
to build wisdom at this time for two
reason first it's because we're living
it in in life like with so many
information and it goes so quick so you
have this reciprocal narrowing were you
just going time from time and you don't
take the step back to see the big
picture of the meta-crisis and also so
so yeah I just leave it there and I let
you comment because I see it as as a
Kairos at least for for our time in our
and my generation so thank you for
explaining it because I have a better
understanding and yeah I don't I don't
think the I agree with you and if I
presented it as otherwise I apologize
because I might have been misleading I
agree with you that I think there's a
synchronicity not to use near term
between this particular biological
crisis and the already existing
meta-crisis I think you're right and I
think it's in in that sense it's a
Kairos in the sense of also being a
tipping point and here I'm talking about
like in dynamical systems where you can
perturb a system for a very long time
and it can it can adaptively restructure
but when the perturbations get too great
it becomes critical and it starts to
break and then that criticality is a
real opportunity in a sense it because
it can go one of two ways the system can
collapse or that criticality actually
breaks the structure up enough that a
new structure can emerge out of it and
so it I agree that I think the virus is
in that sense it's it's sort of a it's
it's it's the you know the proverbial
straw that's breaking the already
overburdened camel's back the the idea
about the urgency because it's very hard
to cultivate wisdom right now I
understand yeah it's very difficult for
people to engage in the practices and
therefore
giving in to kind of urgent short-term
scarcity thinking is going to come very
naturally and so it's I think it's going
to be a very significant challenge as
you said to get people to step back and
see the bigger picture I here's where a
lot of you know a lot of practices a lot
of psycho technological practices are
really important people a way to do this
without having to argue at great length
with people and we already have
independent evidence from this control
level theory is to get at them
practicing things like the stoic view
from above that transformation of
perspective all knowing really does have
a huge impact on people's propositional
and inferential thinking and it also
opens them up to a kind of reciprocal
opening it opens them up to a kind of
wonder in which they're willing to call
their worldview and their sense of
identity into question precisely because
of the way the practice alters what is
normally an unchallenged salience
landscape in which their own particular
urgent narrative is super salient and
blinding them to the bigger picture now
you understand I'm not prophesying that
this is going to spread you know
throughout the culture or anything like
that but what I'm saying is there are
things we can offer people even in their
urgency that are designed to work right
now in the urgency and can ultimately be
made conducive to and coherent with much
more long-term rational processes thank
you
thank you that was an excellent question
and thank you for for explaining it to
me better youth you clarified it very
well sorry for my confusion also but I
love you work I love your framework I'm
using it all the time really
yep psychoactive and powerful thank you
for your work well thank you thank you
for your question I appreciate a lot
Erin Rogerson you had something about a
digital Church
[Music]
uh Aaron would you like me to read it
out hi can you hear me now yep okay the
pandemic is prompting a lot of us to
come together online and I've been able
to skip around to different philosophy
meetup groups really easily that have
been forced to move online very suddenly
and make a lot of really interesting
connections in a very short time people
seem unusually open donor bol going to
connect right now and the technology
like zoom is keeping up with this pretty
well and seems like it will only get
better so I'm wondering if the religion
that is not a religion is something that
will gain traction might it be something
that is primarily an online phenomenon
like that almost like a digital Church
or it's not thirty I can't really see
that now sorry I just was apologizing
that I could do dropped you as I
apologized I'm sorry apologize for my
apology that's an excellent question and
I think that I think that's right Minoo
and Jordans been talking about that
Jordan Hall and he's perhaps the person
to talk a little bit more about he's
talking about not only the the way the
virtual world can afford this he's also
talking about the fact that you know we
might be able to get it to integrate
with some machine learning to really
optimize the way in which we're
connecting and the way we commit some of
the connections can be made outside of
sort of individual cognition and so I
think there's a tremendous potential for
the technology I would like I would like
to point out something that it's also
connected to your question and
strengthens your point and this came up
with somebody was talking it was just
you know doing an online wisdom lecture
for web of wisdom and this came up sort
of this issue about that this technology
does something there there it brings
with it a phenomenological difference
that is actually really important with
and here's a couple of phenomenological
features that came up in the discussion
I was having with this person notice how
close your face is in terms of the size
it fit it fills on my visual field and
yet normally if I was that close to you
and you mean you and I just met
would be like oh but it's okay in this
medium it's part of the grammar and so
there's there's this right there's this
kind of a phenomenological intimacy
notice that also we're sort of
equidistant from each other because we
you know because we're not actually
spatially oriented we're and we're in
this digital space where everybody sort
of has equal access and that's a really
really interesting phenomena because it
also right removes a lot of the typical
ways in which people are marking
identity and status by their spatial
positioning that sort of removed and
it's put into the background in a deep
way now I was talking about that either
way this really enhances the this
technology it's not only what I'm trying
to say it's not only the way the
technology furthers the communication
gives us access it's also transform it
in it's also transforming a
phenomenological experience in a
profound way and I think I suggested to
her that's only a suggestion I'm making
to you but I think it's the only thing
that's analogous to us and people are
also but we're also doing this before
the crisis in our heritage is people
sitting around a campfire because when
people are circling around the campfire
they sort of have that circular distance
from each other and because of the way
campfires their faces tend to be very
well lit and they all are oriented and
Matt Rossano actually talks about that
in Supernatural selection how that
really probably drove our cognitive
evolution a very powerful way because
we've had fire across several species in
a drove working memory it drove our
orientation it probably he said we said
we probably gained the ability to
meditate from sort of sharing the focus
of the fire and then looking up in this
intimate fashion to people's faces so I
think we're doing virtual camp firing or
something like it right here right now
and so it's not just sort of the the the
increased power of communication and
connection I think the medium also has
the potential if properly used
artistically and dialogic Lee to really
tap in to that phenomenological
difference and that primordial right
association and greatly empower what
you're suggesting
the ability for people find something
more like a church because I think
before there were ever any churches
there was the religio around the
campfire for several species and for
hundreds of thousands of years
hmm thank you I just want to add
something I noticed with I have a meetup
group and we meet every two weeks and
going to zoom has actually greatly
improved our ability to have a meeting
in a way that surprised me because I
would have thought you opposite I was
like zooms not gonna work but everything
seems much easier it flows this better
way we're kind of jamming it is better
the way yes I think it's a campfire
effect yeah I think I really do I'm sort
of trying to sort of coin that the
virtual campfire effect and what's
interesting is the contrast to online
teaching where that's normally met like
online lecturing so pretty clearly the
evidence shows that if you go to like an
online university you don't get as good
an education as if you do it in person
so it I don't have anything to say about
that I just want it was a note that
because I agree with you when we're
doing this dialogic thing we seem to
find this this virtual stuff enhances
enhances the process but when we're into
sort of the dissemination the
traditional dissemination of information
in sort of you know a propositional
largely propositional format you seem to
you seem to find a significant
degradation in what people get from it
okay thank you John your hero keep it up
thank you for your encouragement yeah so
Dan Feldman you had a question yes I had
a question our first first professor
fare-bear by aki bareback ii i really
enjoyed your series and it's kind of
inspired me to create my own my own
series that i'm thinking about doing
call me done please come John a you John
yes yeah yeah basically just transition
awakening from the system systemic
inertia is something so my question is
what I'm an American so what can we do
and and other people in similar
situations what can we do to ensure that
the ideas and practices that are
selected in response to this Kairos move
into a wise and regenerative direction
of reciprocal opening yeah and not into
an ignorant and extractive direction a
reciprocal narrowing in light of the
fact that the techno managerial elites
and power are coming forward with a
doubling down a further privatization
austerity yeah
and because there's a there's a bailing
out they're moving to a bailing out of
the corporations and not to some kind of
ubi or or to helping out the spreading
precariat and the small businesses and
such yeah sorry I just I'm just yeah I'm
just like yes everything you're saying
and I this a similar thing came up in
the rebel wisdom thing it came up in a
really interesting way because I was
posed a question and it was an honest
question it wasn't somebody being
manipulative or anything and they
basically said well you know who's
approached you have you been approached
by any of the you know the power holders
about any of it you know and I thought
about it I thought no not a single one
I've not been approached by any of the
people that will power I'm not saying
that the Prime Minister should call me I
mean me or the people I'm talking with I
don't know of anybody that's been a pro
now are lots of other people approach
well here we are here's your answer
like I I am busier now than I was when I
was you know going into work at the
university more and more people are
reaching out more and more people like
so the bottom up is Titanic overwhelming
and the fact and this is why I'm worried
about the Kairos right and why I'm
worried about the doubling down on this
pandemic the fact that the powers that
be seem to be completely oblivious to
this whole dimension and even to the
dimension of meaning in well-being right
uh it's just
that that is something that causes me to
be that's when I think the Kairos is
gonna steer very negative in that we're
going to get a doubling down and we're
gonna get let's get everybody back let's
get everybody back to work let's get
everybody you know let's get let's get
things back to normal as fast as
possible because that's the way with no
no no no no no right that's that's the
way we're gonna do a deal with this um
and so I I share your concern so what
I'm gonna answer now is an answer in
terms it's a moral answer which is
different from a probabilistic answer I
think the moral thing for me to do is
doing what I'm doing which is reaching
out offering trying to get skills trying
to get people talking giving people
resources educating them right getting
people to seriously challenge the
obviousness of common sense seriously
challenge you know the status quo
cultural comp Cardinal grammar I think
that is the right thing to do and I
think it's the right thing to do for
some of the arguments you've already
heard me give is there an opportunity
here that heightens the chance that that
will get games in traction and succeed I
think there is do I predict that it's
going to succeed no I don't I suspect I
hope one way but I suspect that we are
going to get as much as we can to clamp
this all down and try and strangle it
off and what we all have to do is keep
these camp fires burning and keep things
going because as I said this is not the
last time we're going to confront this
and the next time things sorry I don't
want to sound overly dramatic but I
think the next time things are gonna
fall apart more and so getting people
getting created more of a bottom-up
resiliency in this system I think is
going to be needed sorry that was a
somewhat
pessimistic answered but I was trying to
give you as honest and realistic an
answer as I can while at the same time
trying to indicate what I think the
moral response is I appreciate that if I
could if I could just add in I'm quite
active in working together on
participatory democracy movements around
the world with extinction rebellion I
reach working with some groups with the
extinction rebellion and trying to
internationalize you know people's
assemblies citizen assemblies building
up that hollow democracy we essentially
have representative oligarchies yes yes
we have to we have to build that
democratic movement but I don't want to
I want to take the floor that's an
important point no no first of all keep
doing that and you know and I think
that's important and there's a there's
there's a way in which my work in your
work converge because as I've been
trying to create both the the language
and the example of shifting from
adversarial processing the
winner-take-all destroy the opposition
back to a shared commitment to the
opponent processing right of the process
that above being a Republican or a
Democrat I'm committed to democracy in
the process of democracy that's where I
think my word and your word actually
converge in an important way now I agree
I agree yeah I'd love to follow up on
this in another forum if possible
sure so Joe you had a question that was
similar about game a and game B if you
still want to ask it just just go off
new sure I wrote in the eyes of regular
people who aren't there excuse me in the
eyes of regular people those who are in
positions of strategic leverage the
heads of industry government education
things like that it seems to be locked
into a sort of game a
fundamentalism it had been for many
decades this is the sort of blue church
idea my question to you is does the game
be crab - what you know about have any
concrete plan from going secondly from
nudging these people's decisions to
actually transforming their framework
because obviously we've heard
individually upgrading our sovereignty
being able to be more effective agents
individually but I don't know if maybe
behind the scenes there have been talks
on how to scale that up if that's at all
possible I mean I'm gonna I mean I'm a
talking with the person who gave us the
gmae gave me blue church Jordan Hall and
part of that is this idea which is the
religion that's not a religion and
coming and trying to come up with a post
religious faith because here's the idea
this is probably the most radical idea I
want to do what like Augustine did as
the Roman Empire is falling he laid the
foundations not single-handedly and I'm
not saying I'm Augustine so please I'm
just using this as an analogy okay but
what they did is they laid the fact they
laid the cultural cognitive grammar for
an entirely different culture and they
stole the culture bottom-up from the
imperial system now it didn't the
imperial system at some point then
clamped down again but nevertheless we
shifted to the middle that we shifted
out of antiquity we shifted to a
different world and so I want to try and
do that I want to try and create the
systems of meaning the the religion
that's not a religion the ecologies of
practices the communities the networks
of communities all of this is already
happening really empower it both in
terms of its grammar give it the best
scientific tools for engineering the
practices and the ecology of practices I
basically want to steal the culture from
the people who have been abusing us for
such a very long time and I usually
don't speak politically you because I
think that political framing is often a
deep misrepresentation of the issue at
least the way in which political
discourse has been as you said it sort
of been ossified and I think this also I
think Dan was pointing out that - the
way it's been ossified in ways that make
choice no longer sort of really relevant
so all right this is my most radical
thing I guess I'm gonna say I want yeah
I want to help steal the culture away
steal it away and do everything I can
and you know Christianity stoled the
culture away from the elites it's time
now if new elites form they always will
but the culture changed and it changed
in an important way and that's what I'm
trying to do right now and that's that's
what I see myself doing with a lot of
these other people that's very noble and
you certainly have a lot of people who
aren't in those positions I mean if
you're amides you've sort of grown up in
the world sort of looks like it's
running backwards so it's hard to even
imagine that it's been that way for
decades prior but this decade certainly
feels like it's going there's going to
be some collision between the sort of
fresh traded emerging game be tights and
the sort of entrenched game a leaders um
the whole point about the the whole
point about the metaphor is we can't we
can't win by playing the game that's
right
and so my way of trying to understand
what it is to not play their game and to
shift over to in a totally different
game to shift the culture it's to steal
the culture and the way to do that the
way we've right the only thing I can get
from history that's been able to do that
are religion but for reasons that I've
articulated I don't want not personally
I mean in terms of the functionality I
don't think the standard model the axial
age model of religion is going to do
what we need in order to steal the
culture as deeply as we need to steal it
hmm John do you have time for one more
question
yes I do Taylor hawk would you like to
read your question yeah thanks I can do
that yeah John I wanted to check with
you I remember you talking about in some
different contexts about like the
urgency unless sort of coming into
contact with our meaning and yep how
I've seen it like growing up and I'm
wondering like do it we'll see you other
way and yeah given the like the
situation and how quickly it sort of
seemed to come up on us obviously lots
of people were raising the flags but it
came out as quickly and given your
having valid suspicions that this is not
the last time it's gonna happen I'm
wondering how are we going to develop or
grow up even more quickly like it seems
even more urgent so that we I don't we
can mitigate this chance of descending
into chaos if you know we have a second
wave of this in a short term we just we
we need to we need to well sort of it
deals with the previous question we need
to accelerate the all the bottom-up and
top-down ways in which we're trying to
steal the culture I mean and you know
well - I mean the work you're doing both
the circling work you're doing and the
attempts to innovate it in ways that you
know that I'm deeply in concert with
about trying to bring back something
like deal dialectic and via logos and
it's sorry I don't want to look like
some sort of Marxist Leninist poster or
something but we you just need to do
more right we didn't we meet we we just
we got it we got to do more we got to
speed up and we have the virtual
campfire effect and we have what's
happening here and we have that many
more people are willing to call into
question the previously unquestioned
authority of common sense and well
that's the way we've always done it kind
of thing and so I mean there is a Kairos
here I like I said I'm not that
optimistic about it turning you know
now but nevertheless I do think it's
gonna road things things are going to be
reassembled but they're going to be a
much shape your ground and that shake
that that's shaking up at the
foundations creates more interesting is
more spaces through which we can weave
this alternative culture that we need to
do so I I mean I don't want to sound
like boxer an animal farm but you know
there's a sense of which we just right
now we've got to do more of what we're
doing and make use of the best of the of
the emerging properties of of the of the
psycho technology to end the cyber
technologies to try and be force
multipliers for this I'm sorry I can't
say anything too profound to your
question it's a really good question but
that's that's that's all I can see to
say right now yeah keep on truckin
thanks Jeff more accelerate I mean so I
mean and that's why Jordan John and I
are talking about this sense of faith
that's about leaning into the
acceleration of change and you know it's
surfing the wave of uncertainty to use
Andy Clark Stern all they used it for
slightly different purposes right but
you know I used the example from Conrad
of the captain Alliston who's the ship
is been right the ship has been swamped
and they're all those sailors are
clinging to the side of the ship and
Alliston stands and he watches any
weights and he's he's watching and he's
sensing the unfolding of the wind and
the wave and then he goes now and he
gives three orders and they do this
stuff and they write the ship that's the
kind of faith I'm talking about
I feel touched hearing that thanks John
Thank You tiller also again really good
to see you
mister so I'll close in a moment but
John is journey a closing thoughts that
you would like to have for this digital
campfire that we are in right now
I hope that my pessimism is only will
only conduce realism and not any kind of
defeatism in people I hope that's clear
because that was my intent and I I I do
think that it's important that we try as
much as possible to not just talk about
this but exemplify a new way of being to
people that these are the function of
these especially because of the
virtuality of it is not just what's
happening here now but we right and we
are also exemplifying a new way of being
a new kind of as I said culture a
culture of Awakening and we have to pay
attention to and take seriously that
responsibility and rule our manner of
discourse is just as important as the
matter of our discourse that's the final
thing I would want to say about them mmm
that's beautiful so in a moment I'll
make some announcements of what's coming
up in the stoah but first John my friend
thank you so much for coming and
delivering this talking your vision
answer Thank You Graham I appreciate it
thank you so much everybody I really
enjoyed this and I really enjoyed the
discussion and just I really I can't
address you all individually because
there's been so many of you but I just
want to say so many of you gave me so
much encouragement and that really
matters to me and I don't mean just in
an equal inflationary way you know let's
put that aside this is often very
challenging for me for a lot of reasons
I'm naturally socially phobic I have
Meniere's disease there's all kinds of
things that could hold me back my
partner was sort of joking with me today
she said you know you're such an
introvert but you really act like an
extrovert there's this problem washed
out there and you do all these
connections and so what I'm saying is
you got the encouragement really helps
me it helps me overcome my introversion
my social phobia deal with my you know
the challenges of manures and so I'm
very appreciative of the encouragement
so I want to thank everybody very much
for that mm-hmm and imagine we'll have
another session at the store with you
John so we can have a round two with
this so tomorrow we have two events
noteworthy at the stoah Jordan Hall is
going to do a situational assessment at
12 p.m. Eastern Time
and I'll send you the the way to bars
repeat everything in the chat box and we
also have an existential dance party at
7 p.m.
Colin Morris from the Zion 2.0 podcast
he's a dancer so he's gonna have like a
group and body dance
there's just quite fun and - yeah and we
have about 11 events lined up just go on
the website sign up for the mailing list
get updates and to lean on the digital
Church and then the digital basket that
we pass around I'm viewing the stoah as
a gift to the world right now that
everyone could freely use and if you're
inspired to give a gift in return it
could be in any form an idea support
just go to the website and go gift
economy at the bottom and you can
provide it there thanks everyone for
coming out today really appreciate it I
think it's all together and doing this
and Wow what time is Jordan speaking
tomorrow it's at 12 p.m. Eastern Time
it'll be recorded if you can't make it
I'll post it on yeah I might be able to
make it I'll have to see things are very
much in flux for me day by today cool
I'll text you about the link thanks
Peter thanks again for inviting me and
putting this together but yeah thanks
again everybody
take care